We’re gonna review a proposition.
Now, if I ever tell you something in enough
detail that you've already heard that you’ve
heard it enough, please tell me because I
can’t precisely remember what I told you.
I know the line of the narrative throughout
the entire course, and we will return to some
things fairly frequently, but I don't want
to tell you the same story three times, unless
you’re particularly compelled by that story.
So let me know.
We’re going to start with a proposition,
and the proposition is that in order to orient
yourself properly in life, there's two classes
of information you have to have access to.
One class of information is information about
the nature of the objective world, and the
objective world is described in a manner - or
the world when it is treated objectively - is
described in a manner that strips all the
subjectivity from it.
That’s the technology.
The philosophical technology that's behind
the Scientific Revolution - involves stripping
the subjectivity from the sense mediated consequences
of certain kinds of actions because when you
lay out an experiment, you're not just talking
about what happened, you're talking about
what you did and then what happened.
And you're supposed to be able to do it in
a way that ensures that if someone else followed
the exact same procedure, they would obviously
observe the same consequences.
And, in some sense, we’re trying to establish
a realm of knowledge that is universally applicable
to people despite their individual differences.
That's one way of thinking about it, and obviously
that works.
Whether or not it works in a Darwinian sense,
we still have to determine because it could
easily be that our development of the scientific
method is what will make us go extinct, under
which circumstances you might consider it
to have been an error.
But it doesn't really matter at the moment
because so far so good, roughly speaking.
Now, people think the world is an objective
place because we can describe it objectively,
and that's a much more debatable presupposition.
It’s partly debatable because it's actually
based on a decision in some sense, rather
than evidence, partly because your knowledge
is finite in every direction in some sense.
So what that means in a way is no matter what
you know about anything, you don't know everything
about that thing.
And so, you kind of ground out in ignorance
at some point.
So what means is you that you have to buttress
your thinking with a set of assumptions that
you don't question or you just end up in an
infinite regress.
One of those sets of assumptions is usually
reality definition sets of assumptions, or
truth definition sets of assumptions, but
the thing is generally no matter what your
theory of reality is, or what your theory
of truth is, there are alternative theories
of reality and alternative theories of truth
that are equally rigorous and that have different
domains of application.
And it’s a very tricky business, so for
example, if you're a reductionist materialist,
you're going to make the presupposition that
brain physiology is more real than emotional
experience.
I suppose that's in some sense because you
can't get access to someone else’s emotional
experiences, at least not directly whereas
you can get universal access to the fundamental
details of someone’s brain physiology.
It’s something like that.
Anyways now, that's still an arbitrary assumption
because the person and you as well are going
to be acting all the time as if your emotions
and motivational states are real and so then
you run into a problem and the problem is
well, how do you know what someone actually
believes?
You listen to what they say or do you listen
to their explicit and well articulated theories,
or do you watch how they act?
And the answer to that is, you make your choice
and generally there are reasons for that.
Now, one of the conceptual tools that I have
found helpful in my attempts to avoid confusion
when dealing with the fact that there are
very many ways of looking at the world is
to start thinking about theories of reality
as tools rather than descriptions and I find
that extraordinarily useful as a metaphor.
If you have a toolbox full of tools, you don't
necessarily try to reduce the utility of one
tool to another and you don't actually complain
that all tools aren't the same.
A wrench isn't a very good hammer, but that
doesn't mean you can criticize it on that
grounds.
You might not want to use it as a hammer,
although you could I suppose, but it’s not
a justifiable criticism, and it looks to me
- and this is something that a psychologist
named George Kelly pointed out as well, although
I think it’s also an element of pragmatic
philosophy is that one set of tools for one
thing, and another set of tools for another
thing.
That’s helpful, that’s helpful.
And then you are also thinking about the sorts
of problems that you might solve with different
forms of tools, and one problem is what are
things made of - in an objective sense let’s
say.
And another problem might be what is the landscape
of experience, and that's more of a phenomenological
problem.
That’s the problem the phenomenologists
set out, and then the other problem might
be how do you, and should you conduct yourself.
And it could easily be that you can't use
the same tool to solve all of those problems,
and I would say particularly true, technically,
when you're dealing with science because science
in its very nature refuses to answer questions
about what it is that you should do, apart
from some implicit assumption that you should
do science which is actually not -
Well that’s actually not a scientific assumption,
by the way, because it’s a moral assumption,
and the moral assumption is that if you conduct
yourself in a scientific manner, things will
be better because why would you run around
doing science to make things worse, although
you absolutely can.
And, we perhaps are, and even if we aren’t,
we still might.
So that's one of the things I find quite interesting
about the scientific endeavor, and this is
something Jung observed was that it had to
be nested in something outside of itself to
be given its motive force.
It had to be nested in a system of moral assumptions,
and the fundamental moral assumption is the
world will be a better place if we conduct
ourselves along scientific lines, because
why do it?
And that's a statement that cannot be analyzed
from within the confines of the scientific
worldview because it doesn't analyze those
sorts of questions.
Now, you can say they're not real, but that's
a stupid answer because - I think it’s a
cop out, maybe it’s not a stupid answers,
but it probably is.
At least it’s a cop out because if you don't
take that question seriously, you can't really
justify engaging in the activity.
So you could refuse to answer it but you're
basically answering it by engaging in the
activity anyways so even if you're not saying
it, you're still justifying it.
Assuming you can draw conclusions from people’s
actions like you can from their statements
- and it’s hard to really dispute that I
would say.
If you're wise, in fact, I think you derive
more conclusions from their actions than their
statements.
So that’s the underbelly of the first proposition,
and the development of that is something like
the means by which information is transmitted
that is relevant to the domain of behavior
is not the same means by which it’s transmitted
- by which scientific information is transmitted.
And we kinda know that too, without any real
debate, I believe, because how old do you
think science is as a technical endeavor?
What would you estimate?
Hundreds of years.
Maybe thousands of years if you’re willing
to give the Greeks some credit, but really
probably not.
Probably hundreds because Aristotle wasn't
a scientist - like he wasn't a bad observer,
but he certainly wasn't an empirical observer,
and no one got science straightened out till
what - Newton, Descartes, Bacon, and you know
there's a handful of other characters who
were thinking around that period of time.
They sort of established the proper methods,
really, and also the philosophy that underlies
it.
It’s not very old.
Six hundred years, you know, five hundred
years.
That’s really nothing.
It’s the blink of an eye.
It’s yesterday, if that.
It might even be an hour ago.
It’s nothing, but obviously people were
transmitting information about how to act
to each other for untold millennia before
that, and it’s probably more like - it depends
on what you're willing to consider transmission
of information, but even octopi couldn't imitate,
and they're the smartest invertebrate.
They’re quite bright, those things.
They only live a couple of years so they can't
really get things going.
They can problem solve.
They can pull corks out of bottles to get
like a crab in a bottle, and if they watch
an octopus - if an octopus watches another
octopus pull a cork out of a bottle to get
a tasty crab, then that octopus knows how
to do it, which is pretty impressive.
And you could kind of see why octopi can kind
of do that because not only do they have a
brain, but they also have little tentacle-y
appendages which allow them to manipulate
things.
So, one of the precursors to being able to
be intelligent in any act of way is that you
have to have tentacle-y appendages so you
can manipulate the world.
At least for it to be anything resembling
what we would consider to be intelligence,
and that's part of the reason dolphins aren't
really as intelligent as people like to think
because what are they gonna do?
They can't build cities with their flippers.
They're kinda trapped in their test tube bodies,
and the same thing applies to whales.
Obviously they have very large brains, and
they're very social, and they can learn, but
whatever their intelligence is, it’s not
like our intelligence because we run around
tearing things apart and putting them back
together and we’ve got the body for that.
So anyways, long before we were practicing
science, we were doing perfectly well, in
a sense, without any real knowledge of the
objective world at all - at least not any
scientific knowledge about the objective world.
So another thing you might observe about that
is that you can survive perfectly well without
knowing any science at all, in an articulated
and developed manner.
Of course animals are in that category.
So, that also, I think in some sense, undermines
the claim of science to anything approaching
a universal truth because obviously life can
get along perfectly well without it.
Now it depends on some degree whether you’re
a Darwinian or a Newtonian.
Perhaps the unwillingness to commence on what
people should do is one feature of modern
science than it is of science in general because
I’m thinking someone like Clifford.
I don’t know if you know his essay on belief.
I don’t, no.
Oh okay, well his maxim is that basically
it’s wrong always for anyone everywhere
to believe anything on his push to evidence.
And he sort of tries to prove it - he’s
a mathematician.
He tries to prove it on a moral basis.
Of course, it’s not scientific.
That kind of claim can’t be scientific but
Yeah, well I mean obviously the people who
began the Scientific Revolution thought of
it as part of a moral movement.
I mean it was part of the enlightenment.
It was part of bringing clarity to our conceptualizations
of the world and that was supposed to be a
positive thing, but the only issue is that
claim seems to be outside of the claim on
science, in some sense.
Anyways, you get the picture with regard to
the argument.
Okay, now the next step might be if you need
or can utilize or there exists information
that is not strictly scientific, one might
be, well, where did that information come
from?
That's a good one.
How is it transmitted?
That's another one.
And the worst of it is, of course, how might
it be verified?
Because one of the issues - one of the things
that scientists have really got down, and
it’s a major deal, is that they can lay
forth a theory of truth and they they can
operate within that theory of truth and pretty
much everyone can agree on what it is.
The more well established the science, the
more that’s the case.
Like people don’t really doubt Einstein’s
- people really don’t doubt quantum theory
anymore, and you guys don’t doubt it because
there you are using your computers and you
wouldn’t be able to use your computers if
quantum theory wasn't right, so it’s certainly
right enough.
But enough more impressively than that, whenever
someone’s tried to prove it wrong, in any
possible way, even in its most bizarre predictions
over the last hundred and some years, it’s
passed every test with flying colors.
So you know, you can make pretty damn solid
truth claims from within the scientific perspective,
but the problem is that it’s a lot harder
to do that from within a moral perspective
and there's all sorts of reasons for that.
One reason might be that there's a certain
amount of situational complexity related to
every moral question that you can't reduce.
For example, imagine if you're a clinical
psychologist and you're listening to two people
who know each other very well, maybe husband
and wife, discuss their last argument.
And you might say - well you might think - well
let's get to the bottom of this.
Let's find out what this argument is about.
You might think, if you were scientifically
inclined, that it is in fact about something
which means that if you investigated long
enough, you can actually figure out what the
facts are, but I actually don't believe that's
true.
And the reason I don’t think it’s true
is this.
Imagine you have a - there’s this old joke
about these two friends.
They're like 85 years old and they're sitting
on the park bench feeding the pigeons, and
one friend says to the other “64,” and
the other guy cracks up and laughs like mad
about that.
Then the other guy says “83,” then the
other guy cracks up and laughs about that,
and some guy’s watching them and wondering
what in the world is going on.
So the person comes over to these old guys
and says what’s the scoop here?
All you’re doing is sitting there saying
numbers to each other and then you’re laughing
uproariously and I just don't get it.
And they said, well we’ve known each other
so long that we’ve heard each other’s
jokes at least a hundred times and so we have
them completely memorized, and so a couple
of years ago we decided we’d just number
the damn things and it would take a lot less
time to tell then and we could laugh more
that way.
So, it’s an interesting little joke because
it sheds some light on the nature of deep
relationships, and if you have a deep relationship
with someone, here’s how you can think about
it.
Imagine you're trying to analyze an essay,
and I’ve actually built an essay writing
module which is on my site - 230 website.
I don’t remember which template it is but
I’ll tell you in a while.
It’s based on this theory of meaning, roughly
speaking, and you should use it to write your
essay because if you do, it’ll be a way
better essay.
Here’s the issue.
If you're reading an essay, where is the meaning?
Well, that’s a hard one because it might
be a hard one.
So, the question might be badly formulated
in some sense because it might be many places.
But, let’s think it through logically.
Well you need the letters if it’s written
in alphabetic script.
So obviously some of the meaning is in the
letters, and then the letters are combined
in certain particular ways and that gives
you some words, and the words are combined
in some particular ways and that gives you
phrases, and the phrases are joined together
in sentences, and the sentences are strung
together in some reasonably coherent manner.
So they kind of go from start to end in a
paragraph, and then the paragraphs are strung
together in a coherent manner to make up the
totality of the essay.
One of the things I noticed when I tried to
figure out how to grade essays and how to
assess them is that you could do a good or
a bad job at any one of those levels.
Like a really bad essay is full of spelling
mistakes, the words are inappropriate because
the person doesn't actually understand them
so they're awkwardly used, the phrases are
put together in a cliched manner, the sentence
structure isn't good.
The sentences aren't even in the right paragraphs,
much less organized properly.
The paragraphs don't flow from one to another
in what might be called - that’s kind of
where the skeleton of the story is.
It’s sort of the most important level in
some sense, and even if that wasn't all wrong
there’s actually no idea there anyways.
And then you can also read essays that have
one or more of those flaws or some combination
of all of them.
So very frequently, I’d read a student’s
essays and this often happens with smart,
creative students who are very badly educated,
and that would be probably fifty percent of
the people in this class, I would bet.
I say that for genuine reasons because I run
a fourth year seminar where I have people
write extensively, so what they do is they
write a four page essay, and then I complain
about it at all those levels of analysis,
and then they write the same essay again in
six pages, and then I do the same thing, and
then I do the same thing and then they do
the same thing in eight pages, and half of
the first essays are terrible.
That's partly because students do triage.
They think, well do I really have to work
in this course?
I’ll try a bit and if I get slapped, I’ll
work a little harder, and if I don’t, I’ll
devote my time to other courses which is a
perfectly reasonable thing to do, but some
of it is just pure inability.
But what is really fascinating is by the end
of the course is that all of the students
are writing well, and it’s pathetic as far
as I’m concerned because it meant that everybody
could have been taught to write ten years
ago but they weren't.
Anyways if you look at this template that
I laid out, then it will help you in this
because it walks you through the process of
writing properly.
So now and then I would read an essay and
everything is wrong about it, but there's
a really smart about it, and knowing this
multilevel idea with regards to meaning, I
can say, look you’re smarter than you can
write.
There's really something here, but here's
all the things that are wrong with it.
Then you get a worse situation in some sense
where everything about the essay is good but
the idea isn’t, and so the words are good,
the phrases.
The sentences are right, and it goes together
but it adds up to nothing.
And those are hard to grade because you give
them a C maybe or a B, cause I’d probably
give them a B, and the person comes up and
says, where did I make a mistake?
It’s like, well you didn't really make a
mistake, you just didn't do anything right,
and that's a whole different problem.
So you think, that’s pretty complex with
regards to an essay.
Where’s the meaning?
But that isn't where the meaning is.
Here, let me give you an example.
I was thinking of this the other day.
So, the ethnicity and the cultural backgrounds
of my students have changed quite radically
over the years.
When I started teaching this course for example
- and my personality course as well which
would have been thirty years ago - I can take
it for granted that everyone in the room would
know the basic biblical stories, and they
would know the Judeo-Christian version of
them and not, say the Islamic version of them.
Well that's gone, and that's really made it
difficult for me in some ways because there's
a bunch of things.
There’s a bunch of collective knowledge
that might constitute a shared set of cultural
assumptions that I can no longer presume and
it means there's all sorts of things that
I can't talk about or if I’m going to talk
about, I have to step way back and start from
first principles let’s say.
So that’s also made me think because if
I - let’s say you write me an essay and
let’s say it’s a Psychology essay.
Now you're gonna presume that there's a whole
bunch of things I know about Psychology that
you also know.
And the reason you're going to presume that
is because, well we come - for the purpose
of this conversation - we come from the same
cultural background and what that means is
we share a set of assumptions, and we don't
have to say what those assumptions are.
We can assume them and then we can talk about
the things that we disagree about, and of
course that's what you're doing when you're
writing an essay or having a conversation
right?
You're saying well obviously we don't have
to talk about what we know because we already
know it.
We want to push that a little bit so we start
to talk a little bit about the things we don’t
know, but no more so than we both understand.
So then you think damn it, the meaning of
the essay isn’t in the essay at all.
It’s in the interaction between the shared
cultural assumptions between the writer and
the reader and the essay.
Well and then you think, it’s worse than
that even because the shared cultural assumptions
are in their own sort of network, and then
that's nested inside a very an extraordinarily
broad biological network and it’s like actually,
you can continue expanding the outer reaches
of the essay without limit.
So part of that means it’s actually impossible
to specify the meaning of the essay.
It’s something you both work at in combination,
as writer and as reader, but it’s very fluid
and flexible.
That problem is partly why the post modernists
got going because they sort of noticed this.
Corrupt as they are, they did notice at one
point that it was very very difficult to say
what any given phrase, paragraph, or essay
mean because it wasn't there - like it’s
not in the book.
It’s sort of in the book, but - you know
this too if you listen to a piece of music.
So let’s say you had a favorite song when
you were fourteen, and when you first heard
that song, maybe you didn’t like it that
much, but you maybe heard it four times and
thought man that’s one excellent song.
Then at some point, you've heard it so many
times that you never want to hear it again.
That’s interesting too because it means
the song has transformed in relationship to
your historical interactions with it and you
might say, no this song is the same.
Well, it depends on what you mean by the song.
The notes are the same.
The experience has certainly transformed.
So anyways, back to the couple that are sitting
there talking.
They're having this argument and they're trying
to sort out what this is about.
Well the problem is it’s about everything
the argument is about plus everything that’s
ever happened to them in their relationship.
If someone has told you the same thing fifty
times, it is not the same thing as the thing
they told you the first time.
God only knows how many transformations it’s
gone through as it’s been continually repeated,
and how many different arguments it’s been
embedded in, and how many things you’d have
to know to understand the shades of intonation
in all of that.
But basically each utterance a couple produces
is - it’s meaning is determined by the entire
history of interactions that those two people
have had.
So, how are you going to specify that?
It’s very very difficult to specify it.
Now, you really can’t, and it’s also difficult
to know when you’ve specified it enough.
You know, one of the things that is interesting
training as a psychoanalyst is that it started
to become absolutely mind boggling how much
archaeology you can undertake underneath a
single statement, especially if it’s delivered
with a bit of edge and some contempt.
It’s like there’s just levels and levels
and levels and levels of meaning underneath
that, and you can tell that when you’re
engaged in an argument like that because someone
will trigger you, let’s say, for lack of
a better word, and they’ll have broken a
rule that you have established with them and
you’re both in a pit.
The fight is about that pit, even though maybe
it’s about some surface thing, and you're
just running around there like rats that are
lit on fire and there’s nothing you can
do about it.
And it’s a consequence of all the issues
that are lurking beneath the surface of that
speech act that seemed to be something - you
could capture it on a video.
You can say, well here’s what you said.
There's a video tape recording of it.
It’s like no, that's not what you said because
the videotape cannot capture the context,
and it can’t.
So you can't even get an objective record
of the meaning of the conversation because
the meaning isn’t right in the conversation.
Okay so that’s one of the problems.
One of the problems we’re trying to validate
moral claims is that you’ve got this insane
contextual complexity that’s almost impossible
to dispose of, and so you can say - you can
even say that if person A did action A in
situation A, that’d be right and then person
B did action A in situation A, that would
be wrong.
It would depend on the person, and so it’s
very easy to slip from that into a kind of
moral relativism because how in the world
do you deal with the complexity and how do
you make a truth claim?
So I would really say in some sense that’s
the intellectual situation in modern universities.
Now, the other thing that’s kind of interesting
is that this was actually discovered in a
number of modern fields simultaneously, so
just as the literary theorists started to
discover, say after World War II, that it
wasn’t enough to say that a book had meaning
in it.
Like there was something wrong with that,
and there isn't even a single meaning, there’s
a multiplicity of meanings and it isn't even
a stable multiplicity of meanings, people
were finding that out in other domains as
well.
For example in artificial intelligence where
it became very obvious, very rapidly that
perceiving a simple object was not simple
because objects aren’t simple, and the border
between one object and another is in some
sense arbitrary.
I mean, when I look at each of you, I sort
of see you as entities, but that’s because
I see you at this level of resolution.
You're cellular masses at a different level
of resolution.
You're molecular composites at a different
level of resolution.
You’re made up of ten times as many bacteria
as cells at another level of resolution, so
really you’re more like an ocean than you
are like an entity.
And then, well is it you or your family that’s
the real.
Or is it you, your family, and your culture?
What about your species, or are you a mammal.
It’s like all of those things and any of
those things at the same time, so when I look
at you, what am I supposed to see?
Do I see individual with name or do I see
ethnicity or do I see - well you get the picture.
So object perception turns out to be extraordinarily
difficult because things aren't just simple
objects even if they’re relatively simple.
So, you throw your hands.
You think how can there be any harmony.
How can you draw some sort of sense from that?
Okay, so that’s the argument against drawing
any sense out of it.
But then, let’s try the other attack.
Let’s see if we can make a case for there
being some claims of - that moral claims can
be validated.
Okay, so here’s a question for you.
If you took a bunch of chimpanzees that didn't
know each other and you threw them in this
classroom, what you would have is a war.
Right.
Now, you're roughly in that situation, not
exactly because A - you’re not chimpanzees,
but you know your genetic material is quite
reasonably related.
You only split off your common ancestors seven
million years ago, and that seems like a long
time and it is, but it’s not three hundred
million years ago.
It’s still relatively recently from the
evolutionary perspective.
Here you all are, you don’t really know
each other.
You obviously share important elements of
identity.
So you’re all students, and you can come
in here and all of a sudden you all know what
to do, and no one fights.
Or if they do fight, it’s - there are very
constrained rules around the fighting and
everyone accepts them, and it seems hard to
say that’s not better than the alternative.
So unless you wanna come in here and have
an absolute chaotic war.
Somehow we’ve managed to figure out how
we can figure out how to bring relative strangers
together in a relatively high pressure situation
because we’re learning about complicated
and challenging things, and everybody gets
along.
And everybody’s kind of happy about that.
So it looks like we can figure out patterns
of behavior that, well, then the question
is, are they correct?
Are they morally correct?
Are they right, or did they work?
And you might also ask yourself what’s the
difference between all of those claims, is
there similarity or difference between those
claims.
So, and then you might ask yourself - okay
so here’s something else you might think
about.
So, let’s say you’re playing Monopoly.
How many of you have played Monopoly in your
life?
Okay, is there anyone here who hasn't played
Monopoly?
Excellent.
A cultural universal.
So, obviously in some ways it doesn't matter
if you get all those little hotels right?
But, on the other hand if you act like it
doesn't matter while you're playing Monopoly,
then people hit you with things and they should
because part of the rule is that you're gonna
act like this matters because if you don't,
then it’s not any fun.
So you have to act like it matters and then
it turns out when you start playing, it matters.
People will actually - they’ll get angry,
especially if you cheat.
But people will play Monopoly.
They’ll act as if the endpoint matters.
You might say, well what is the endpoint?
And one answer is to get all the hotels and
all the money, so you enter the 1%, so you
have all the wealth and no one has any, and
so you win and you feel happy about that,
even if you're a radical left winger.
So that's kind of interesting.
Then you say, well that's not really the point.
The point is to enjoy the game, and you say
yeah okay that’s probably the point too.
And you might say, well that's not really
the point either.
You want to hone your negotiating skills.
You want to spend some time with your friends.
There's lots of things going on at once, but
it doesn't really matter because Monopoly
is a game that you’ll play.
Now imagine instead that Monopoly - here's
the new rule for Monopoly.
All the people you're playing with can randomly
steal your hotels and houses and your money
whenever they want, and you can steal it back.
So then you think, well no one’s gonna play
that game, and then you think well why not?
Well, the first surface answer is that’s
a stupid game, and you know that somehow.
You think that’s a stupid game, but then
you start to think about well why is that
a stupid game?
Or you might say it’s an unplayable game
which would be a little bit more sophisticated.
Why would that not work?
And you might say, well what’s the point
in getting all the hotels if someone could
just take them?
But you might say what’s the point in getting
the hotels anyway?
Like who cares about the damn hotels.
So it’s a bit tricky.
There’s something about the randomness of
what’s now allowed and the unpredictability
of it and the arbitrary nature of it and its
lack of a relationship with your own actions
that takes all the motivational impetus out
of the game.
So one thing we might think about to begin
with, is there’s a difference between a
good game and a bad game, and there's also
a difference between a game and no game.
And we don’t know what the difference is
exactly, but there is a difference.
We might even say not only are there good
games and bad games, some good games are better
than other games.
How many of you have played Settlers of Catan?
Okay, is that better than Monopoly or worse?
Student says: It’s better.
better.
Does anyone think it’s not better?
Okay, why is it better?
What’s better about it?
It’s more complex and the part where you
said - I mean it’s not necessarily stealing
but there’s a piece of the game in there,
I think it’s like the robber or something
like that.
Yeah, there’s a robber.
Student says: And you place him on one of
the tiles.
You can mess with people, so that’s fun.
It is fun.
It’s like I’m gonna get you with a robber.
It’s more akin to real like I think, like
in Monopoly
No, that’s reasonable.
It’s also got a strategic element.
How many of you play Risk?
Okay, Settlers of Catan or Risk?
Okay, two Risk diehards.
What about the rest of you?
How many are for Risk?
Two.
How many for Settlers of Catan.
Okay, okay.
Well, Settlers of Catan is a bit like Risk
because it has a strategic element and there's
a territorial expansion that goes along with
it, and there’s also trading which is one
of the things that's nice about Monopoly and
about Risk.
Okay but well, you can see - you have intuitions
about what constitutes a better game and part
of the way you develop those intuitions is
not exactly philosophical because I doubt
if you really thought through why Settlers
of Catan is a better game than, say, Risk
or Monopoly for those of that think it does,
but you watch your own reaction and your own
reaction is okay well I’d rather play Settlers
of Catan.
You might ask yourself why, but you don’t
have to.
You’d just rather play it.
So then you think well what does it mean that
you’d rather play it?
Well it’s more fun, it’s more enjoyable.
If asked voluntarily, that's the one I would
pick, but you really don't know why, apart
from those reasons but obviously those are
complex - that’s a complex social engagement,
those games.
They’re complex.
In fact they’re so complex, you can have
preferences and not even know why, and that’s
interesting.
I think the idea that there are games, good
games and bad games and games and non-games,
is a nice way of starting to conceptualize
what the difference might be between moral
systems because a game is actually a moral
system.
It has a point.
It has an end.
You have to cooperate and compete to run through
the game.
So awhile back, a psychologist actually started
this and it’s reprehensible, but psychologists
have done lots of reprehensible things and
this is one of them.
This psychologist, whose name I don't remember
at the moment, was reviewing the literature
on the difference in aggression between boys
and girls and men and women.
Boys and men are much more aggressive, depending
on how you define as aggressive, than girls
and women.
Now that tends to be mostly true with physical
aggression.
So you might say kicking, hitting, biting,
punching, stealing.
Two year old boys for example - two year olds,
the ones who do most of that are boys.
Now, the two year old girls are cutting each
other up behind their backs but no one measures
that.
So you find for example, with female aggression
it tends to be relationship savaging, and
you see that in the playground.
You see it in junior high.
You see it in high school, and you see it
on the net.
It’s always the same thing.
Whether men are more aggressive than women,
it depends on how you define aggression, but
men are more physically aggressive anyways.
Awhile back, there was this idea that maybe
we could dampen down the male aggression by
socializing little boys more like little girls,
and one of the offshoots of that was that
we should only let children play cooperative
games.
Now, the first thing you might notice is that
anything you might have done as a game was
not cooperative.
Right, like it’s not a game if it’s just
cooperative, but then the other thing you
might notice is that the distinction between
a cooperative and a competitive game is far
more sophisticated than people that come up
with those dimwitted theories of how to improve
the world would ever appreciate.
So here’s an example.
Is hockey a game?
Yes.
Is it an aggressive game?
Is it a competitive game?
Yes.
Is it a cooperative game?
Aha.
Why?
Why is it a cooperative game?
Because you have to work together.
Right, so there's the team right.
You’re also obviously cooperating with your
team members, but you're also maybe trying
to be the best player, but you're also trying
to be the best player in a way that doesn't
irritate the hell out of your team players
right, because there's something about that
that’s counter productive.
Like, even if you're a good player and you’re
a prima donna and you hog the puck, say, and
maybe you're not interested in the development
of your other team members, like you’re
not a good player even if you are the most
talented.
So, there’s obviously a cooperative element.
Is there a cooperative element beyond that?
Well yeah, you have to all agree to sort of
cooperate in so much as agreeing to the rules
of the game and playing it.
Right.
You don't bring a chessboard or a basketball.
No matter if you're on different teams because
you're all there to play hockey.
So just to play hockey is a cooperative endeavor
because think of all the other things you
could be doing instead of playing hockey at
that time.
You could be doing an infinite number of other
things so really if you look at the relationship
between cooperation and competition in any
collaborative human affair, things are usually
competitive at one level, cooperative at another,
competitive at another, like there’s this
continual interplay between competition and
cooperation and you can't disentangle them.
Now one of the things that Piaget said - Piaget
is a, for those of you who don’t know and
you probably all do know, is perhaps the foremost
developmental psychologist of the 20th century
even though he didn't think he was a psychologist.
Piaget actually made the claim, the radical
claim, that two year olds for example - this
isn’t Piaget’s claim but it’s associated.
If you put people together, and their age
matched.
So you got a group of nine months olds, say,
one year olds, two year olds, three year olds,
all the way up to eighteen, and you just throw
them in a room, maybe with some things of
them to do and you count the number of violent
acts, which is kicking, hitting, biting, or
stealing.
Okay, two year olds, they’re the most violent
human beings and most of them aren't actually
violent.
There's a subset of them that are violent.
It’s about five to ten percent of them,
and almost all of them are boys, and then
if you track those boys across time, over
the next two years most of them become civilized
and the ones that don't never become civilized.
So they're kind of antisocial throughout their
childhood, and then when testosterone kicks
in at about fourteen and all the boys get
antisocial again, they catch up to the always
antisocial boys and the normal boys taper
off quite dramatically at around nineteen
and flatten right out at about twenty seven
but the antisocial boys, they just keep being
antisocial.
So now, Piaget noted that there was a dramatic
transformation in behavior - individual behavior
- in relationship to the social world between
the ages of two and four.
And, if you watch two year olds play together,
what they did fundamentally is like a parallel
play.
So maybe, there's one two year old there and
another two year old there and that two year
old is playing truck and this two year old
is playing ambulance or something or maybe
playing doll, and they're sitting with each
other, and maybe they interact a little bit
but they're not playing the same game.
Okay so, what they're doing in some sense
is they're engaged in a goal directed activity,
and it has a point.
They're sort of integrating all their interior
sub personalities in a sense that allows them
to play a single game with themselves.
That's pretty complex from a cognitive perspective
because they're not fractionated, and they're
not being pulled out by hunger or anger or
sadness or fear or any of those things, and
they're doing something that's highly complex
cognitively and they can organize themselves
well enough to do it for a substantial period
of time.
So it’s like it’s a major developmental
advance.
But they can't do it with another person.
Now one of Piaget’s hypotheses was that
they couldn't do it - they couldn't play the
same game with another person without actually
setting up a competitive structure so actually
competition was a prerequisite to competition.
The idea was okay so, if you watch how kids
do this, you can get a sense of it.
I mean, on the one hand they all get together
and they decide how to play tag.
Everyone knows the rules for tag, and you
can win at tag, but without the point - the
point in some sense is the construction of
a dominance hierarchy of competence.
Someone wins and then there are sort of the
people who are second best and third best,
and everybody's really into doing that.
You all have to get together if you're kids
and you say well what should we do.
You decide, well, we’re gonna play tag and
then you set up the rules because there’s
infinite variations of tag, and everyone goes
off and play.
So it’s a competitive game because only
one person can win, or maybe one at a time
can win.
But once you’ve all agreed on that, then
you’re cooperating.
So that’s quite interesting, and Piaget
regarded that as a necessary stage of the
ability to act like a social creature.
Here’s something that happens if you’re
not a very popular kid.
Let’s say four kids are playing Jacks.
Good enough.
I don't think kids play Jacks anymore but
whatever.
If they were playing Jacks, they’re sittings
there playing Jacks, and when you play Jacks,
you bounce a ball and you pick up a jack,
and if you manage that and a ball - if you
manage that, you drop the ball and pick up
two jacks and drop the ball, and you keep
going up till like eight jacks or whatever.
So now another kid wants to play Jacks, and
we’ll say this is a relatively popular kid
and so the kid sidles up to the group that’s
playing and sits down because they're all
sitting down and then watches, and then maybe
watches jack-playing motions or a couple of
comments about how the Jacks game is going,
and maybe the other kids don't have to disrupt
what they're doing very much and they can
kind of open the circle, and let that kid
scoot in and he gets to, or she gets to play
Jacks too.
Whereas a kid that doesn't - and that often
doesn't happen, even if it’s a popular kid.
Sometimes the little group that's already
formed won’t open and let them in.
You've been to cocktail parties.
It’s exactly the same thing.
So you’re supposed to hang around the edge
of the conversation and maybe if you've got
something that isn't too stupid to say, you
can offer it and maybe they’d let you in.
Okay, now if you're maybe not very social,
what you do is stand out there and you don't
notice what the hell is going on and you don't
start to match your body to what’s happening,
and maybe you say, I don't want to play Jacks,
that's a stupid game.
Let's go do something else, in which case
the kids are not happy with you, and you're
unpopular.
And that’s that.
You're stuck with it because if you've got
that by the time you’re four, the other
kids are gonna leave you so far in the dust
you’re never going to catch up.
Okay, so what have we concluded from that?
We might conclude that people play games.
There's lots of different games.
There’s lots of different playable games.
There might even be an infinite number of
playable games.
There's a lot of non playable games, those
are the ones that aren’t any fun, and there's
a lot of interactions that aren’t games.
Okay so we can all accept that, and then we’ve
added to that the observation, or the presupposition,
the ability to play games is a prerequisite
for being socialized, so being able to operate
together with people and that that operation
has elements of competition and elements of
cooperation.
Reasonable?
And then you might say, well everything people
do communally has a game like aspect, and
you might say well that's actually why kids
like to play games because kids play games
because games are a simplified analog of life,
and if you get good at playing games - well
what happens is that the games you play are
increasingly complex and more and more real
world like until they're actually indistinguishable
from acting in the world.
But they're even then they're still games
in a sense because they could - the rules
could be different.
But then, you might think well are there things
that couldn’t be different?
Well, yeah there are some things.
It’s gonna be cooperative.
It’s gonna be competitive.
There's gonna be rules.
Everybody needs to agree on the rules.
People have to want to play.
This is something else Piaget observed.
It’s bloody brilliant.
He thought well, how can you decide if one
game is better than another.
Let’s say that's a moral claim in a sense,
but he wanted to narrow it down so that it
was possible it could be answered.
What he said was imagine you have group A
that was attempting to obtain a goal, and
group B that are attempting to attain a goal.
Both groups have agreed that attaining the
goal is valuable.
We don’t have to argue about the value of
the goal.
We’ve settled that.
Okay now, we’re going to make a further
assumption which is all things considered,
getting towards the goal with less effort,
more enjoyment, and less trouble would be
better.
Okay, you have to take that as a given because
it might not be.
Sometimes something difficult is better.
Well then you might say okay, would people
working voluntarily or involuntarily be more
likely be able to reach that goal with less
misery faster and more effectively.
Piaget’s answer was if you could get people
to play the game voluntarily, you don't have
to waste effort on enforcement, no one kicks
back so the system is going to be more efficient
across time.
Now that’s smart because he’s got a way
of conceptualizing what might constitute a
better system.
Now it’s grounded in subjective experience
in some degree.
Less misery, more enjoyment, but there's also
a way of measuring it.
It’s also more efficient, or it does what
it’s supposed to do with less noise and
grief.
Less cost, let’s say.
So that’s pretty smart.
Okay, so then let’s make another - well
how old do you think kids games are?
And I don’t know what’s happened to kids
in recent years because their culture has
somewhat been seriously disrupted by television
and computer, but you guys are a lot younger
than me.
Did you play hide and go seek?
You know ring around the rosie?
You know that.
Do you know what that is?
You don’t know Ring Around the Rosie.
How many people don’t know that.
Ring around the rosie, pockets full of posies,
hush ah hush ah, we all fall down?
Okay, how many know that.
It’s an English nursery rhyme.
It’s about the plague.
It’s about the black plague by the way.
And so, that piece of doggerel, that piece
of rhyme has been around, transmitted by the
oral culture of children since the time of
the black plague.
And so a lot of children’s tradition is
in the oral tradition, and a lot of the games
children play are passed along by children.
Kids learn how to play hide and go seek.
And how many of you played tag?
Anyone never play tag?
Right, so everyone plays tag.
How would you conceptualize tag if you were
a biologist?
What do you think children are doing?
They’re hunting.
They're chasing things down, obviously.
They're chasing things down.
Now hide and go seek, that’s a tougher one,
but it’s certainly exploration.
They’re exploring the landscape, and they're
matching wits with one another, but - and
they're also trying to see if - you know,
do people like you enough to actually find
you, which is a helpful thing to know if you're
four years old.
So anyways, children pass these games down
across the centuries.
Maybe tag is one of those games you don't
even have to pass down.
Children might just invent it spontaneously
with every generation because you can more
or less play tag with a dog.
I mean, the dog doesn't quite get it, but
it’s close.
Okay, so there are some games that are enjoyable
enough that they're either transmitted and
everyone knows them very rapidly, or they're
so close to our nature we can just reinvent
them and I think tag is the classic example
of that.
So that’s interesting too because what it
means is that there’s certain types of competitive
and cooperative behavior.
Those are elementary moral systems that are
- they look like they're integral to our nature.
You can even say they're built right in, or
you might say they're so close to built in
that it doesn't take much of an introduction
for the roles of the game before everybody’s
pretty happy with it.
You see this with a lot of things.
You play peek-a-boo with a baby.
Okay so what are the rules?
What are the rules of peek-a-boo.
You cover your eyes.
Okay so that’s right.
You go like this.
Okay then what’s the next rule?
That’s right.
You reveal your eyes.
You don't just sit there like this.
Now you can play a trick on a baby if you
want, and babies will laugh about this sort
of thing which is really, I think, quite amazing.
A baby’s laugh is something remarkable to
me.
So you can go like this, and then like this
and then like this and then like this and
then you can do this, and the baby will laugh
because that's a little variation eh.
Or you can go like this.
Right.
And then the baby - well that’ll even make
you guys laugh.
That’s good, you can see how deeply rooted
this is.
So you know but, eventually what’ll the
baby do?
It’ll grab your hands, pull them down because
you're breaking the damn rules.
And the baby knows the rules even though you’ve
never established any rules, and you can get
the rules going with about five reps.
You say okay, this.
Maybe no one’s ever played peek-a-boo with
a baby.
The baby figures it out right away.
This, this, and then you vary that.
Maybe do that.
That baby thinks that’s a hell of a good
joke, you know, cause you went up instead
of down, and so it’s variations within this
rule bound theme.
It’s kind of musical in a sense, there’s
variations in the theme.
Now what you don’t do is go.
Waahh!
Cause that’ll just short it right out.
So you don't do that unless you’re, you
know, unless you have an evil streak in you.
So there's certainly ways of violating the
baby’s expectations and what the baby will
do if you do that is startle and they startle
with their whole bodies, and then look at
you and probably they’ll burst into tears.
But some babies will just laugh like mad if
something like that happens, and you can find
those babies all over YouTube, right, because
you get the baby that the mother sneezes and
the baby has a fit laughing for like ten minutes.
But it’s quite interesting.
One of the things about babies that I’ve
never been able to understand is the staggering
sophistication of their senses of humor.
Like it’s deep eh?
Cause even a nine month old baby can play
tricks on you.
So, you know they're baby tricks, but still,
they’re tricks and they laugh and they're
quite comical and they like variation.
Anyways, the point is - one of the points
of all this is this understanding of game
like structure is really really really really
really really deep inside of us, and it’s
way before articulation.
It’s way before we can say the rules.
Babies can pick up the damn rules right away
and it’s kind of a dance in some sense,
and a dance is also a rule bound structure.
If you’re dancing with someone well, there’s
rules, but don't step on their feet but you
also set up a set of expectations in the dance
and you violate them in tandem.
And if you can do it gracefully, it’s fun.
Maybe the person you’re dancing with is
an absolute klutz and so autistic you can’t
even get outside of yourself, and might make
a half reasonable partner or if it’s just
hopeless.
But the dance is the same thing.
It’s not negotiated verbally.
It’s negotiated bodily, and unless we’re
able to imitate, and imitate insanely well
because human beings can imitate like mad,
because we won’t be able to do that.
So babies are the same way.
You basically start - you don’t actually.
Peek-a-boo doesn’t have rules because a
rule is a stated description of a set of expectations.
What peek-a-boo has is expectations and repetition,
and you can violate the expectation but that
doesn’t mean you’re violating a rule because
an expectation is not a rule until you observe
the expectation, you describe what it is and
maybe even write it down.
You can play games long before you can follow
rules, and one of the things Piaget observed
is if you watched kids play a complicated
game like marbles and they're like six, and
you take them out of the game and ask them
what the rules are, they can't tell you or
they might get some of them right and a bunch
of them wrong.
Maybe if you interviewed every child that
was playing, and you looked at the commonality
of the descriptions, you could extract out
the underlying rule structure of the game.
But the kids don't know the rules.
What they know is how to play with other kids
when they're playing marbles, and a lot of
that’s nonverbal hints and eyebrow raises
and no you can’t do that and so forth.
It isn't much later until they can tell you
the rules, if ever.
So like, you know, you guys can't tell me
the rules for dancing successfully with someone.
You can tell me some stupid things you shouldn’t
do, but imagine how complex it is.
It’s very difficult to articulate out the
whole structure, but you can sure tell when
it’s happening, and you can sure tell when
you’re not doing it or when your partner
isn’t.
So partly what that also means is you know
how to do things you don't know how to do,
and you know how to all sorts of things you
don't know how you know how to do.
In fact, most of what you know is like that.
That also means we can be playing games that
are extraordinarily sophisticated that we
don’t understand, but that doesn't mean
- well we can't describe at least.
We don't have an articulated knowledge of
the structure, but we can still play them.
Now, I don't know if you know this or not.
You might know it.
A while back, twenty years ago - about that.
Those massive online multiplayer games started
to become popular, and some of them - I think,
although I don't know this for sure - some
of them lasted a long time, and maybe some
of them still being played, like the early
ones.
So they developed entire worlds in there and
you know, there was an economist who became
quite famous because of those games.
Castronova, I think his name was.
Edward Castronova.
I think that’s right, but it’s close.
Anyways, he thought hey look man those aren’t
games, those are countries.
So one of the things he tried to do was calculate
their gross national product, and you know,
you can trade items in those little worlds
and you could sell them on eBay.
For awhile in this one game, and maybe this
still happens, there were young people in
the Philippines who were working inside these
games making artifacts that they were selling
on eBay to other game players because they
could make more money doing that than actually
working in the actual world.
So Castronova - I think was his name - said
well you don't get it.
That is the real world.
It’s not a game, or if it’s a game it’s
so much like the world that it’s part of
the world.
So he calculated the gross national product
of some of these massive games, and they were
like the 30th richest country in the world.
It was insane.
So that’s interesting because that also
shows you that the line between a game and
reality is not clear.
Here’s another example of that.
Something worth thinking about.
Some of you have no doubt played very complex
multiplayer online games, and I suppose those
are often adventure games or quest games and
you have to communicate with other people
and you have to solve problems and maybe you
have to defend yourselves, like you're in
an exploratory party in a new world.
Something like that.
So it’s pretty sophisticated, and okay some
of you have worked at McDonald’s or another
fast food restaurant.
How many of you have worked at a restaurant.
How many at a fast food restaurant.
Would you say that an online game is more
like the world, or less like the world than
your job at a fast food restaurant.
More.
It’s more.
Anybody disagree?
Okay, why is it more like the real world?
Because you’re doing more complex stuff.
What are you doing?
You’re exploring.
You’re thinking.
You’re getting out of situations because
new ones are always coming up and you're dealing
with them and you’re learning.
Fast food is like you're doing - Right, you’re
a real cog in a fast food machine.
Yeah, but it’s in the real world.
Is it a game?
You’re more like a machine in the fast food
part.
So does that mean McDonald’s is less real
than a multiplayer online game?
Well it’s a tough one, eh, because when
you’re trying to think about what real means,
is you might think maybe I phrased that wrongly.
Maybe I could say is McDonald’s a worse
model of the real world than a multiplayer
online game?
And it’s hard because it’s hard to say
McDonald’s isn’t part of the real world
so a priori, the claim is kind of absurd.
It’s like well, you’re in a building.
People actually come there.
They give you money.
It’s real.
But then, well you think about these complex
games and you’re practicing an extraordinarily
sophisticated form of social and intellectual
behavior and we actually don’t know what
that does to people.
Maybe it makes them extraordinarily sophisticated
and social.
I do think it helps with introverts quite
a lot because it’s harder for introverts
to become extremely socially fluid because
people wear them out.
A lot of introverts do a lot of heavy duty
socializing on the net, and in my experience
it’s been, all things considered, probably
a plus rather than a minus.
With regards to your use of computational
devices, one of the things I used to see my
kids doing is they would sit together in a
group.
They were teenagers, and there’d be a bunch
of friends that weren't there and while they
were interacting with all their friends who
were there, they were also interacting with
all their friends who weren’t there.
Is that a common thing for teenagers to do?
You’re texting your friends and so forth.
Is that reasonably standard behavior?
How many of you have done that?
Okay how many of you have done that regularly?
Okay, how many of you haven’t done that?
Okay, so most people have done it but not
everyone.
For those of you have done it, is that more
advanced or less advanced social behavior?
More.
Okay you think more.
Why?
Cause you’re keeping your friends in the
room while they’re not there.
So it’s like they have a conceptual idea
of what you’re doing and it’s like - they
understand where the group dynamics are moving
towards without them actually having be there.
Okay, do you think that you paid a price for
it in the decrease of the interactions you
were having with the people that were actually
there?
Not really.Yes.
You think so.
Okay, how many people think they do pay a
price for it?
How many people think they didn’t?
Okay, so - well let’s start with you guys
then.
Why did you think you didn't pay a price for
it?
Well because I feel like it really doesn't
take that much time to just text and go back
to talk to your friends.
Okay.
Well I think that you can pay a price, but
if you’re doing it correctly and you’re
monitoring the conversation you're taking
a part of, you can see when it would be appropriate
to text someone else which probably means
you're paying more attention to the people
you're talking with because you're also texting.
Okay so you’re kind of taking a multitasking
rationale for it in some sense, although assuming
you have to also heighten your attention to
manage that.
There’s people who didn't think - that you
did pay a price for it.
Who thought that?
Okay, what sort of price?
I think that especially when you're texting
people, there's so much complexity that gets
lost in translation, like you don't really
convey your feelings, like there's so much
more to use than language.
Okay then they certainly lose something.
What about you, while you're interacting with
your actual present friends?
I would say you have to commit some certain
amount of effort to writing a text, you ignore
aspects of - for example, they’re asking
about something and then you go and text the
person and you come back and miss some part
of the conversation.
Yeah, so it’s like kind of -
Yeah so it’s kind of like start, stop, start,
stop.
I don't think you can one hundred percent
commit yourself to -
Well one of the things you suggested was that
some of that can be mitigated by doing it
properly, which implies there's an emergent
norm for doing this sort of thing and that
if you're good at complying with the norm,
then you’re not irritating people and maybe
you can handle both things at once.
Something like that.
But if it’s properly to the people who are
there, is it proper for the friend who is
waiting for you to answer?
Well I guess one answer to that is that’s
up to them to determine, like if they don't
want to be part of it, they can do something
else.
The reason I’m saying that specifically
is that you can imagine that’s how the norm
develops.
It’s like obviously if a successful norm
is going to develop that allows text conversation
and real world conversation to occur at the
same time, everybody has to want it to happen.
That means if you can’t do it in the manner
that everyone wants, it’s going to die out.
Now see, that's another example of how you
can see how moral structures - I think - might
evolve, is the right way of thinking about
it because I think moral structures evolve.
And I think they’re just as real as anything
else that evolves.
Now, evolved things can be staggeringly complex.
Just think about how many lifeforms there
are, and how many niches there are for their
lifeforms and so you have in some sense an
infinite variety, but it’s not infinite,
and it follows patterns.
Not just any old thing can be alive, and not
just any old thing can be social.
Here’s an example, and I found this out
awhile back.
I did a lot of neurobiological research.
Some of it hands on, a lot of it conceptual
especially in the early days of my graduate
work.
I got really interested in the function of
serotonin.
You all know, undoubtedly, that one of the
things antidepressants do is decrease the
rate at which serotonin is pulled back up
into the neurons that deliver it and that
seems to help stabilize people’s negative
emotions.
Makes them less volatile, less anxious, less
likely to withdraw, and so - or you could
say it makes them more confident.
Now we also know if you say we look at a chimp
hierarchy, you take bottom chimp and you give
him anti-depressants, he looks a lot more
like top chimp.
So, because the bottom chimp world is a very
dangerous place.
It’s very uncertain.
He doesn't have a place to sleep.
He doesn't have high quality mates.
He doesn't have good things to eat.
He’s stressed man, it’s bad down there.
So maybe that's part of the reason his nervous
system is tuned so that he’s more anxious
and upset by everything because everything
is more dangerous.
Part of that’s modulated by serotonin.
Okay, so here’s a rough rule.
If there’s a hierarchy in an animal kingdom,
as you move up the hierarchy, your serotonin
levels increase and as you move down the hierarchy,
your serotonin levels decrease and that’s
somewhat independent of your absolute wealth.
So here’s a famous experiment.
It’s called the White Hall experiment and
it was done on English bureaucrats, and the
thing that’s so cool about the White Hall
experiments is they were done fifty years
apart.
So what they showed basically was - imagine
you take an English bureaucracy and you stratify
it by position.
Englishmen are hierarchical, and so you stratify
You have the top people and the bottom people
and what you find is the bottom people die
faster and more often.
You might say if you're not that healthy,
you end up at the bottom.
Fair enough, but there seems to be an effect
above the effect of just general health.
It’s worse to be at the bottom than at the
top.
Okay, that was true 70 years ago, and another
study was done 50 years after that.
Now the thing that’s so cool is by that
time, from a material perspective, the people
at the bottom of the modern hierarchy were
at least as wealthy as the people who were
like two thirds of the way up 50 years before
because everybody had running water, everyone
had enough heat for the winter, you know.
Everyone had shelter, and so on.
So you figure, with regards to wealth, once
you’ve got running water, reliable shelter,
heat, and maybe air conditioning if you live
in the desert, and you’re not hungry, you’ve
got ninety percent of what wealth can deliver.
Really, all things considered.
The rest of it is just status and luxury items,
but the relationship between position of status
and death rates remain constant.
So that’s very interesting, and we know
that that’s true from a lot of other studies
as well.
It’s like control for absolute wealth, there’s
still problems with hierarchy, and that seems
mediated at least in part by serotonin, and
serotonin regulates negative emotion, and
the more negative emotion that you experience,
the more cortisol you produce, and cortisol
in high levels is toxic and suppresses your
immune system so your brain gets damaged,
and you gain weight and you get diabetes,
and maybe develop Alzheimer’s disease and
are maybe more prone to cancer and heart disease,
and that’s just not good.
Now that serotonergic mechanism is really
old, and so you can give serotonin injections
to unhappy lobsters and it cheers them right
up, at least behaviorally speaking.
If they're defeated in a fight, and you give
them a serotonin injection, they’ll stand
up tall, confident and they’ll fight again.
I’m telling you that for a very specific
reason.
One of the things we’ve been asking about
is well how might you conceptualize moral
systems and how might you conceptualize evolution?
One of the propositions was there are playable
games and non-playable games.
Well here’s a playable game.
Dominance hierarchy.
We’ve been playing it for four hundred million
years.
It’s stable.
Now, it’s so stable that even lobsters have
them, but even worse is that the biochemical
systems the lobsters use act within the dominance
hierarchy and react to, it’s the same in
us.
And so, not only is that stable, it’s well
ridiculously stable.
So one of the things we could say is that
one of the games that seems emergent and real
is a dominance hierarchy.
And then we might ask what exactly constitutes
a dominance hierarchy, and we might ask well
what constitutes a highly functional hierarchy
versus a dysfunctional hierarchy, and even
what does highly functional and dysfunctional
mean.
Well we have to define all those terms.
We will, as we move forward.
But the point I’m making is - and this is
a bit of a contradiction with the initial
system I made with the tight distinction between
the scientific world and the objective world
because I’m also talking about the evolution
of games, and you know, the study of evolution
is a scientific study and the dominance hierarchy
is a biological phenomena and so in some sense
it’s also a game, and it’s also a moral
structure and so there are levels of analysis
where these things start to get tangled together,
and that’s partly what we’ll try to sort
out.
So, we’ll do that in the future because
it’s very very complicated.
Alright now we’re gonna step back a little
bit.